const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Which one of the following was a proponent of humane and moral treatment of insanity?","options":{"A":"Anton Mesmer","B":"Phillipe Pinel","C":"Jacques Lacan","D":"Emil Krapelin","E":"Melanie Klein"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Phillipe Pinel (1745–1826) was working at Salpetriere in Paris at the time of the French Revolution. He insisted on releasing patients from chains in asylums, emphasized systematic clinical observations using case records and championed humane treatment of the mentally ill. Anton Mesmer was a proponent of mesmerism, a form of clinical suggestion. Jacques Lacan is known as the ‘French Freud’. Melanie Klein was an object relations theorist. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 17."},{"question":"Morel was a French–Austrian physician associated with the term demence precoce. He is also associated with which of the following theories?","options":{"A":"Regeneration theory","B":"Devolution theory","C":"Degeneration theory","D":"Segregation theory","E":"Integration theory"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Degeneration theory maintained that most forms of insanity resulted from continuous deterioration of mental faculties. More alarmingly, it also stated that hereditary transmission of nervous dysfunction was produced by noxious environmental factors. Morel was the proponent of degeneration theory. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p.19."},{"question":"Neurasthenia was originally described by which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Beard","B":"Freud","C":"Jung","D":"Adler","E":"Engel"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"American neurologist, Beard, described neurasthenia in 1880. This is retained in the ICD-10, and is the closest diagnosis to the present day chronic fatigue syndrome. Various terms, including myalgic encephalomyelitis and viral fatigue syndrome, are in vogue in an attempt to emphasize infectious/ infl ammatory origin of this illness. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 21."},{"question":"Inducing malarial fever was proposed as a treatment for which of the following diseases?","options":{"A":"Hysteria","B":"Neurasthenia","C":"Tourette’s syndrome","D":"General paralysis of the insane","E":"Multiple sclerosis172 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"General paresis or paralysis of the insane (GPI, also called as paralytic dementia) is a rare encephalitic illness. GPI was common in the past due to syphilis. Malaria therapy for GPI was proposed by Wagner von Jauregg, a Nobel laureate. Manic presentation was common in GPI. GPI has almost disappeared now, though with the rising HIV pandemic it is speculated to have resurgence in the future. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 21."},{"question":"Which one of the following hormones was used to induce coma in the treatment of schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"Thyroxine","B":"Cortisone","C":"Testosterone","D":"Insulin","E":"Parathormone"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Insulin coma therapy for severe mental illness was introduced by Sakel in 1933. This was a potentially fatal treatment complicated by seizures and encephalopathy. Chemically induced seizures were also employed around the same period (von Meduna) for treating schizophrenia. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 21."},{"question":"Who among the following described hebephrenic schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"Greisinger","B":"Falret and Baillarger","C":"Tuke","D":"Hecker","E":"Clouston"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Hecker described hebephrenia – characterized by adolescent onset with disorganized behaviour and incongruent affect. Hecker was a pupil of Karl Kahlbaum, and some consider that he only popularized the notion of hebephrenic schizophrenia, which was originally proposed by Kahlbaum. Sir Thomas Clouston is associated with ‘developmental insanity’. William Tuke opened the Retreat in York, promoting moral treatment and unchaining the insane. Falret and Baillarger are associated with folie circulaire (manic depression) while Greisinger developed views on tha neuropathological basis for psychiatric disorders. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 3.184 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which one of the following terms was coined by Esquirol?","options":{"A":"Nymphomania","B":"Monomania","C":"Hypomania","D":"Pseudomania","E":"Pyromania"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Monomania was described by Esquirol and it is similar to the present day concept of delusional disorder. Nymphomania was coined in 1775, by a French doctor Bienville, from Greek nymphe meaning ‘bride’. It was used to describe excessive sexual desire seen in some women. The term hypomania was coined by Mendel (1881). Bynum B. Monomania. Lancet 2003; 362: 1425. Angst J, et al. Toward a re-defi nition of subthreshold bipolarity: epidemiology and proposed criteria for bipolar-II, minor bipolar disorders and hypomania. Journal of Affective Disorders 2003; 73, 133–146."},{"question":"First-rank symptoms in schizophrenia were proposed by","options":{"A":"Kurt Schneider","B":"Carl Schneider","C":"Manfred Bleuler","D":"Eugen Bleuler","E":"Emil Kraeplin"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Kurt Schneider proposed fi rst-rank symptoms – neither diagnostic nor prognostic but only indicative of schizophrenia. Eugen Bleuler used the term schizophrenia in 1911. Carl Schneider classifi ed many forms of formal thought disturbances; later he was closely associated with the Nazi movement in Germany, promoting ‘euthanasia’ for mentally retarded and epileptic patients. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 568."},{"question":"All of the following are correctly matched EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Ribot: anhedonia","B":"Sifneos: alexithymia","C":"Kahlbaum: cyclothymia","D":"Moreno: chorea","E":"Cameron: overinclusion"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Moreno described psychodrama, not chorea. He also introduced sociometry. Anhedonia stands for inability to obtain pleasure from activities; alexithymia is a diffi culty in verbalizing emotional states; Cyclothymia, retained in ICD-10, is a minor subsyndromal form of bipolar illness described by Kahlbaum; Cameron described overinclusion as a part of formal thought disturbances. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1446."},{"question":"The fi rst antidepressants to be discovered were","options":{"A":"SSRIs","B":"MAOIs","C":"TCAs","D":"Amphetamines","E":"BenzodiazepinesHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS 173"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Monoamine oxidase inhibitors were the earliest antidepressants. They were serendipitously discovered when iproniazid, an antitubercular antibiotic, was found to have mood- lifting properties. This was reported by Bloch in 1954. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1293."},{"question":"Case studies have been traditionally useful in studying brain–behaviour relationships. In one of such case study Phineas Gage, a railway worker, sustained damage to which of the following brain areas?","options":{"A":"Parietal lobe","B":"Hypothalamus","C":"Pineal gland","D":"Frontal lobe","E":"Temporal lobe"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Phineas Gage was a railway workman whose frontal lobe (especially the ventromedial prefrontal area) was accidentally drilled out by an iron bar. He survived the terrible accident but had signifi cant personality and behavioural change, stimulating interest in studying functions of the frontal lobe. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 133."},{"question":"Lithium was used in which of the following medical illnesses before being rediscovered for mania?","options":{"A":"Gout","B":"Osteoarthritis","C":"Epilepsy","D":"Stroke","E":"Goitre"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lithium was brought to the attention of psychiatric practice in 1949 by Australian, John Cade, who highlighted its mood-stabilizing effect. Lithium water was a popular ‘tonic for aches and pains’ and was used for gout before this discovery. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 256."},{"question":"Which one of the following is the oldest treatment method employed to cure mental illness?","options":{"A":"Electroconvulsion","B":"Coma induction","C":"Trephination","D":"Lobotomy","E":"Rest cure"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Trephination refers to drilling holes in skulls to release evil spirit that were believed to haunt the insane. This practice is noted even in prehistoric skulls dated 6500 BC. Electroconvulsion was introduced by Cerletti and Bini in the early part of the twentieth century, while Moniz proposed neurosurgical methods to treat psychiatric disorders. Rutkow IM. Moments in surgical history – trephination: how did they do it? Archives of Surgery 2000; 135: 1119.HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS 185"},{"question":"Durkheim is a name associated with the study of which of the following phenomena?","options":{"A":"Homicide","B":"Violence","C":"Truancy","D":"Arson","E":"Suicide"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Durkheim described anomic, altruistic, and egoistic suicide. In anomie, the patient feels let down by society and fails to follow norms. In altruistic suicide, over involvement with a particular social group leads to signifi cant alteration in one’s self identity and the suicide is for the group cause rather than personal cause, for example hara-kiri of a soldier. Egoistic suicide refers to those suicides in people who are not strongly integrated into any social group, for example lack of family integration in unmarried persons. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 900."},{"question":"Which of the following is a correct match with respect to diagnostic scales in psychiatry?","options":{"A":"Negative symptoms: Jaspers","B":"Akathisia: Barnes","C":"Frontal battery: Folstein","D":"MMSE: Andreasen","E":"Formal thought disturbance: Hare174 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Barnes’ Akathisia Rating Scale is used to measure akathisia, a side-effect of antipsychotics characterized by both subjective and, later, objective restlessness. Folstein described MMSE in a seminal paper; Andreasen devised the Thought Language and Communication scale to measure formal thought disturbance; Kay’s PANSS (positive and negative symptom scale) can measure negative symptoms; Hare is a name associated with a psychopathy checklist used by forensic services. Barnes TRE. The Barnes akathisia rating scale – revisited. Journal of Psychopharmacology 2003; 17: 365–370."},{"question":"Which one of the following is regarded as an illustrative case for classical conditioning in phobia?","options":{"A":"Little Hans and horses","B":"Little Albert and rabbit","C":"Anna O","D":"Daniel Schreber","E":"Ratman 17 . Who among the following used the term agoraphobia to describe a category of anxiety disorder?"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Little Albert learnt to avoid rabbits after a loud noise induced fear in him whenever he played with a white rat. This fear later generalized to white rabbits (Watson and Rayner 1920). Anna O was a patient with ‘hysteria’ treated by Freud and Breuer. Ratman was also a patient of Freud who had OCD, while Schreber had delusional disorder. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 142. Watson JB, Rayner R. Conditioned emotional reactions. Journal of Experimental Psychology 1920; 3: 1–14."},{"question":"Who among the following used the term agoraphobia to describe a category of anxiety disorder?","options":{"A":"Burton","B":"Schneider","C":"Westphal","D":"Jung","E":"Anna Freud"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Robert Burton wrote ‘The Anatomy of Melancholy’ in which some description of symptoms suggestive of agoraphobia is seen together with the account of depressive illness. In 1871, Carl Otto Westphal coined the term agoraphobia to describe several of his patients who experienced severe anxiety when walking through streets or open squares. Schneider proposed fi rst-rank symptoms; Jung belonged to the psychoanalytic school. Anna Freud, Freud’s daughter, was involved in classifying defence mechanisms and also in child psychoanalysis. Callard F. ‘The sensation of infi nite vastness’; or, the emergence of agoraphobia in the late 19th century Environment and Planning: Society and Space 2006; 24: 873–889."},{"question":"Freud is regarded as the father of psychoanalysis. Which one of the following techniques was developed by Freud for his own clinical practice?","options":{"A":"Narcoanalysis","B":"Polysomnography","C":"Free association","D":"Dissociation","E":"Mesmerism"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Free association was a popular technique used by Freudian analysts. Having learnt hypnosis from Charcot, neurologist-turned-psychoanalyst Freud developed the method of free association in which patients were encouraged to speak about their thoughts without distraction or censure. This was intended to be a therapeutic method, though later adapted largely as an interview technique. Narcoanalysis involves using barbiturates as truth serum. Dissociation is a psychological mechanism and not a clinical technique. Mesmerism or animal magnetism was developed by Anton Mesmer. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 5."},{"question":"Phrenology refers to the study of which of the following concepts?","options":{"A":"Study of free will","B":"Study of conscience","C":"Study of logic","D":"Study of skull contour","E":"Study of homunculus"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Phrenology was a popular theory which claimed to determine personality and diagnose/ predict mental symptoms using the shape of the skull. It was developed by the German physician Gall and was very popular in the mid 1800s. Phrenologists used their bare hands and palms to feel for fi ssures or dents in their patients’ skulls. With this information, the phrenologist would report on the character of the patient; its popularity reached extremes when marriages and recruitment were advised by phrenologists. Simpson D. Phrenology and the neurosciences: contributions of F. J. Gall and J. G. Spurzheim. Australia and New Zealand Journal of Surgery 2005; 75: 475.186 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Schizophrenia was coined by Bleuler in 1911. The literal meaning of the term schizophrenia is","options":{"A":"Split mind","B":"Split skull","C":"Fused mind","D":"Exploded will","E":"Split will"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The term ‘schizophrenia’ stands for split personality. Even today this is confused with more dramatic multiple personality disorder by some of the lay public. The term was coined by Eugene Bleuler in 1911. It is derived from the Greek words ‘schizo’ (split) and ‘phrene’ (mind). Bleuler intended to use the name in order to capture the functional dissociation between personality, thinking, memory, and perception in a patient with schizophrenia. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 568."},{"question":"Which of the following refers to the literal meaning of the term hysteria?","options":{"A":"Wandering mind","B":"Wandering kidney","C":"Wandering uterus","D":"Wandering brain","E":"Wandering heartHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS 175"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The term hysteria stands for ‘wandering uterus’. It was incorrectly observed that hysteria affects only women. The uterus is a major morphological difference between a man and a woman; hence, rather simplistically, it was believed that uterus was the site of problems in hysteria. Also it was believed that unmarried women often had this wandering uterus that could be tied down by wedlock, leading to a reduction in hysterical symptoms following marriage. It was even believed in a Greek myth that this wandering uterus could strangulate a person, leading to hysterical globus or aphonia! Unusual treatments, including pelvic massage to induce orgasm, were offered to cure hysteria later in history. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 634."},{"question":"Which of the following diagnostic technique involved injecting air into subarachnoid space?","options":{"A":"Myelography","B":"Pneumoencephalography","C":"Electroencephalography","D":"Encephalotomography","E":"Encephaloultrasonography"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Dandy, in 1919, used pneumoencephalogram as a diagnostic technique to visualize the brain. This technique showed enlarged ventricles in patients with schizophrenia, which was later confi rmed by investigations using various other imaging modalities that developed later. There was a high fatality rate associated with pneumoencephalogram. Semrad EV and Finley KH. A note on the pneumoencephalogram and electroencephalogram fi ndings in chronic mental patients. Psychiatric Quarterly1963; 17: 76–80."},{"question":"In a large, multicentre trial reported in 1988, Kane demonstrated that clozapine was superior in treatment-resistant schizophrenia patients compared to which of the following drugs?","options":{"A":"Haloperidol","B":"Chlorpromazine","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Fluphenazine","E":"Thoridazine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Kane revived the use of clozapine through his milestone study. He compared chlorpromazine and clozapine in a treatment-resistant sample and demonstrated clozapine’s superiority in this instance (in 1988) leading to FDA approval (in 1989). The multicentre trial showed that 30% of clozapine-treated patients will respond in 6 weeks while 60% will respond in 6 months. On the other hand, only 4% improved on chlorpromazine in combination with benztropine. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 262."},{"question":"Who is the proponent of primal therapy?","options":{"A":"Arthur Janov","B":"Melanie Klein","C":"William Tuke","D":"Franz Alexander","E":"Mary Ainsworth"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Primal therapy refers to a trauma-focused treatment proposed by Arthur Janov. Primal therapy claims that only through direct experience of pain and emotions, could any psychological treatment work. Other talking therapies use higher cortical cognitive processes to talk about emotional experience while primal therapy attempts to engage lower brain centres during psychotherapy. Janov A. Towards a new consciousness. Journal of Psychosomatic Research 1977; 21: 333–339."},{"question":"Which of the following described delusions as un-understandable?","options":{"A":"Jean Piaget","B":"Erik Erikson","C":"Karl Jaspers","D":"Eric Fromm","E":"Aaron Beck"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Jaspers was both a psychiatrist and a philosopher. He studied psychopathology in depth; the descriptive psychopathology and psychiatric phenomenology used in current psychiatric practice are largely Jasper’s contributions. According to him, a specifi c quality of delusions is their ‘un-understandability’. This distinguished primary delusions from delusion-like ideas or secondary delusions that arose out of a different psychopathology. for example hallucinations. Jones H et al. Jaspers was right after all – delusions are distinct from normal beliefs. British Journal of Psychiatry 2003; 183: 285–286. see also Owen G et al. Jaspers’ concept of primary delusion. British Journal of Psychiatry 2004; 185: 77–78.HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS 187"},{"question":"Choose the best explanation for the term spirituality:","options":{"A":"Affi liation to a religious group","B":"Habitual practice of any religious activity","C":"Submission to existence of supreme powers, for example God","D":"Deeply held beliefs about the meaning of life","E":"Religious orientation without discrimination"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Contrary to widely held belief, spirituality is not defi ned as affi liation to religious practice or accepting God. It rather refers to deeply held beliefs about the meaning of one’s life. Kay J and Tasman A, eds. Essentials of Psychiatry. Wiley, 2006, p. 23."},{"question":"The International Pilot Study on Schizophrenia concluded that global, cultural, and social differences exist in which one of the following characters of schizophrenia?","options":{"A":"Core symptoms","B":"Severity","C":"Outcome","D":"Dose of medications","E":"Gender distribution176 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The IPSS (International Pilot Study on Schizophrenia) was a global, multicentre study carried out by the WHO. The main fi nding was a strikingly similar core symptom profi le irrespective of cultural differences and more or less similar life-time morbid risk (though this has been disputed; See McGrath NAPE lecture 2004). Surprisingly, outcome of schizophrenia was better in the developing, rather than the developed countries. McGrath JJ. The surprisingly rich contours of schizophrenia epidemiology. Archives of General Psychiatry 2007; 64: 14–16. McGrath JJ. Myths and plain truths about schizophrenia epidemiology – the NAPE lecture 2004. Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 2005; 111: 4–11."},{"question":"Which one of the following psychopathologies is infl uenced more signifi cantly by cultural differences than the others listed?","options":{"A":"Delusions","B":"Somatization","C":"Hallucinations","D":"Mania","E":"Obsessions"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Somatization is consistently found to be higher among South Asian populations, especially in females. Linguistic differences could explain an apparent inability to verbalize emotions, leading to requests for medical interventions for physical symptoms. Cultural sensitivity is essential to detect undiagnosed depression in different ethnic groups. Bhui K and Hotopf M. Somatization disorder. British Journal of Hospital Medicine 1997; 58: 145–149."},{"question":"When using interpreters during psychiatric interview it is best NOT to","options":{"A":"Explain goals of the interview to the interpreter","B":"Rotate different interpreters with the same patient","C":"Provide debriefi ng to the interpreter after an emotional clinical encounter","D":"Enquire about the interpreter’s country of origin or social position","E":"Encourage literal translation of the Mental State Examination"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Using different interpreters for different sessions of clinical encounter with the same patient will lead to confusion and needless anxiety due to the presence of a new person during each doctor– patient meeting. It is advisable to stick to the same interpreter when dealing with a particular patient. Knowing the interpreter’s social and ethnic background might help in utilizing the interpretation better. Also, the Mental State Examination can be misinterpreted by a lay person – it is often necessary to instruct the interpreter to translate certain parts of the clinical interview verbatim. Kay J and Tasman A, eds. Essentials of Psychiatry. Wiley, 2006, p. 27."},{"question":"Clinical samples of patients with anorexia nervosa show a trend towards which of the following social categories?","options":{"A":"Upper social class","B":"Lower social class","C":"Immigrant population","D":"Poor literacy","E":"More elderly parents"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"An unequal distribution of social class is noted in anorexia. Higher representation from upper classes of society, good literacy rates, and higher frequency of non-immigrant populations is noted among clinical samples of anorexia patients. This strengthens the aspect of culture specifi city of anorexia nervosa. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 836"},{"question":"Sick role includes all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Excuse from social responsibility","B":"Expectation to seek help","C":"Taking blame and responsibility for the illness","D":"Perception of disease as undesirable","E":"Attempts to restore previous state of health"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Sick role, as defi ned by Parsons, excludes patient from taking all responsibility for becoming ill. It is perceived that illness is unavoidable and any ill person must seek help, as illness is undesirable and an attempt must be made to restore the previous state of health. Untill this happens the person is relieved of certain social responsibilities. This social perception of illness drives a person to occupy what is collectively termed as the sick role. Kay and Tasman A, eds. Essentials of Psychiatry. Wiley, 2006, p. 679."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT a component of high expressed emotions?","options":{"A":"Warmth","B":"Over involvement","C":"Critical comments","D":"Enmeshment","E":"Hostility"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Enmeshment has not been discussed as a component of expressed emotions (EE). Enmeshment stands for deranged family dynamics, characterized by blurring of normal hierarchy and intergenerational boundaries in a family. Enmeshment is linked to various child psychiatry problems, including eating disorders. EE is characterized by warmth, hostility, and critical comments and emotional over-involvement. High EE is implicated in relapse of various psychiatric illnesses, especially schizophrenia. It is also demonstrated that being on long-term antipsychotics can alleviate the relapse-provoking effect of a high EE environment to some extent. Vaughn and Leff studied EE in depth. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 603. Leff J and Vaughn C. Expressed Emotion in Families. New York: Guilford Press, 1985.188 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"High expressed emotions could be measured using which of the following instruments?","options":{"A":"Camberwell Assessment of Needs","B":"Camberwell Family Interview","C":"Simpson Angus Scale","D":"Quality of Life Scale","E":"Caregiver Burden ScaleHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS 177"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Camberwell Assessment of Needs scale, also called as CAN, was developed by the Section of Community Psychiatry (PRiSM) at the Institute of Psychiatry. It is a tool for assessing the needs of people with severe and enduring mental illness, including both health and social needs. It has clinical and research versions, and also a shorter version for routine use. The Camberwell Family Interview is a different scale from CAN, and assesses the feelings and experiences of relatives with regard to a patient’s admission to hospital. In the Camberwell Family Interview, three measures of EE – criticism, hostility, and emotional over-involvement – are assessed. Leff J and Vaughn C. Expressed Emotion in Families. Guilford Press, New York, 1985."},{"question":"Effects of high expressed emotions could be mitigated to some extent in which one of the following situations?","options":{"A":"The contact with family is less than 35 hours a week","B":"The family members are having mental health diffi culties themselves","C":"The patient is married","D":"The patient has comorbid depression","E":"The patient has chronic rather than acute schizophrenia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"It has been shown that the effect of high expressed emotions on relapse of psychotic episodes is lesser if contact with family members lasts less than 35 hours a week. This dose– response relationship adds strength to the role of the family’s emotional expression on the course of schizophrenia. The degree of EE can be higher if any of the family members has mental health diffi culties themselves. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 404."},{"question":"Association between crime and mental illness is diffi cult to study. This is due to which of the following reasons?","options":{"A":"Most criminals are mentally ill","B":"Criminals are deceptive about mental illness","C":"Crime is over reported","D":"Captives are not representative of all criminals","E":"Mental illness is rarely independent of the crime committed"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"It is widely acknowledged that captives may not be the ideal, representative sample of everyone who indulges in criminal activity. Captives may be a special population with lower than normal skills to escape or avoid a sentence or arrest. Often the IQ of captured criminals may be lower than the IQ of non-captured criminals, on average. So studying captives for the rate of mental illness or effect on crime secondary to treating mental illness could not be generalized to wider social criminalities. Most criminals are mentally sound. Crime is under-reported rather over reported, on the whole. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 703."},{"question":"Stigma associated with mental illness could potentially be reduced by all of the following interventions EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Destigmatization campaigns","B":"Increasing community living of severely mentally ill people","C":"Educating the public about mental illness","D":"Legislation against social discrimination","E":"Improving broadcasting standards"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Various measures to combat stigma has shown only modest benefi ts over the century. Destigmatization campaigns, public education, and vigilant media policy can be helpful. It is clear that in the past few decades, the closure of asylums and psychiatric hospitals has increased community living of patients with mental health problems. But this has not translated into lower rates of stigma and discrimination – if anything this has got worse, assuming different forms. Byrne P. Stigma of mental illness and ways of diminishing it. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2000; 6: 65–72."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT true with respect to stigma against mental illness?","options":{"A":"Stigma leads to social exclusion","B":"Stigma can prolong the duration of depression in a patient","C":"Stigma is seen even against mentally ill professionals","D":"Stigma has reduced substantially in the last two decades","E":"Stigma perceived by patients varies with their diagnosis"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Stigma has not reduced in anyway over last two decades in spite of improved literacy rates. The perceived stigma is more generic for mental illness and does vary with the diagnosis to some extent. Stigma leads to delayed help seeking and social exclusion, making outcome worse. Byrne P. Stigma of mental illness and ways of diminishing it. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2000; 6: 65–72."},{"question":"The term acculturation refers to which of the following?","options":{"A":"Adoption of beliefs and values of one cultural group by another","B":"Migration of civilizations in need of food and shelter","C":"Adoption of civilized social norms by a culturally weaker group","D":"Acceptance of rules and regulations of a mental health institute","E":"The tendency for a cultural group to enforce their values on another group"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Acculturation is a social–anthropological phenomenon which refers to the adoption of cultural practices of one group by another due to the effect of living close to each other. It does not refer to being civilized or non-civilized in cultural practice. The tendency for a cultural group to enforce their values on another group is called assimilation. Acceptance of rules and regulations of a mental health institute is related to the process of institutionalization, described by Goffman. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 168. Goffman E. Asylums. Essays on the social situation of mental patients and other inmates. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1961.HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS 189"},{"question":"Koro is an anxiety state seen most commonly in which of the following geographical zone?","options":{"A":"Latin America","B":"South-east Asia","C":"India","D":"Alaskan natives","E":"Siberia178 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Koro is a culture-bound syndrome that is most often seen as genital retraction anxiety rather than delusional state. It usually affects young males, and is accompanied by anxiety that genitals are shrinking. It is an acute condition with favourable prognosis compared to chronic psychotic illnesses. It is often reported in Malaysia, Taiwan, Philippines, and other parts of south-east Asia. It is referred to as Shook Yang in Japan. Koro literally means head of a turtle (which retracts). Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1062."},{"question":"Which one of the following is a culture-bound syndrome characterized by an exaggerated startle reaction in middle-aged women?","options":{"A":"Piblokto","B":"Latah","C":"Brain fag","D":"Windigo","E":"Susto"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Latah is a culture-bound syndrome seen mainly in women in south-east Asia. It is characterized by severe startle response together with loss of control over behaviour, echolalia, and echopraxia. Such patients are noted to obey any commands issued to them. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1063."},{"question":"In the UK, the annual prevalence of hallucinations is higher in which of the following racial groups?","options":{"A":"Asians","B":"Caribbeans","C":"Americans","D":"Whites","E":"Australian Jews"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The prevalence of ‘all cause’ hallucinations are higher in the Caribbean population living in the UK compared to other ethnic groups. It is noted to be 2.5 times more common in this group. South Asian migrants come next in the list, followed by native White populations. Cultural differences exist not only in disease prevalence but also in non-clinical but abnormal mental experiences measured in community samples. Johns LC, Nazroo JY, et al. Occurrence of hallucinatory experiences in a community sample and ethnic variations. British Journal of Psychiatry 2002; 180: 174–178."},{"question":"Which of the following is true regarding increased incidence of schizophrenia among migrant population?","options":{"A":"It depends on the country of origin","B":"It could be explained by drug use","C":"It is due to genetic factors","D":"It is generation limited","E":"It is strongly related to lower socioeconomic status"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"It is now accepted that immigration is a clear risk factor for developing schizophrenia, irrespective of the prevalence rates in the country of origin, genetic loading, or cannabis use. This effect is not limited to the generation that migrates – it extends to the second generation immigrants as demonstrated in the AESOP Study in the UK. It has also been shown that in neighbourhoods where minority status is signifi cant due to the high population of majority ethnic group in the locality and poor socioeconomic status of immigrants, incidence of schizophrenia is increased. This applies to any minority group irrespective of racial status. Cooper B. Immigration and schizophrenia: The social causation hypothesis revisited. British Journal of Psychiatry 2005; 186: 361–363."},{"question":"Which of the following theories holds that mental illness is a result of societal infl uence?","options":{"A":"Causation theory","B":"Drift theory","C":"Labelling theory","D":"Social disintegration theory","E":"Social agent theory"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Labelling theory was applied to explain mental illness in 1966 by Thomas Scheff. He claimed that mental illness is manifested solely as a result of societal infl uence. The society views certain actions as deviant. A label of mental illness is placed on those who exhibit deviant behaviours in order to explain these behaviours. The expectations then placed on these individuals unconsciously change their behaviour – giving them the role of mentally ill. Social causation and drift theories attempt to explain the association between lower socioeconomic status and mental illness. Social causation theory proposes that low socioeconomic status breeds mental illnesses. Social drift theory takes the view that a decline in social status occurs following development of mental illnesses. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 123."},{"question":"A patient with learning disability cannot understand the implications of hospitalization. But he does not resist being admitted to a hospital. Which of the following best describes his mental capacity status?","options":{"A":"Compliant and capable","B":"Compliant but not capable","C":"Non-compliant and incapable","D":"Non-compliant but capable","E":"None of the aboveHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS 179"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Often patients who lack capacity to make treatment decisions agree to follow a treatment plan passively. This special group is termed ‘compliant not capable’. Learning disability services, dementia care, and geriatric care often face challenge with such patients. The Bournewood case refers to a patient with autism who was kept in hospital against the wishes of his carers as he complied with hospital admission. Though he did not have capacity to decide on his treatment he was not detained under the mental health act as he was compliant to stay at the hospital. This case revealed a wide gap in English mental health law. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 36.190 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A patient decides to be on the waiting list for 12 months untill she could see a psychotherapist. Choose an ethical principle relevant to this scenario:","options":{"A":"Confi dentiality","B":"Distributive justice","C":"Therapeutic privilege","D":"Non-malefi cience","E":"Autonomy"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Justice is one of four primary ethical principles. Justice is the moral obligation to act on the basis of fair judgement between competing claims. Justice is classifi ed into: (1) fair distribution of scarce resources (distributive justice); (2) respect for people’s rights (rights based justice); and (3) respect for morally acceptable laws (legal justice). In health ethics, distributive justice means equity for all where ‘equals are equally treated’; it concerns economic distribution and health- care resource allocation. Gillon R. Medical ethics: four principles plus attention to scope. British Medical Journal 1994; 309: 184–8."},{"question":"A test for capacity to make treatment decisions includes all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Ability to understand the choice","B":"Belief in the information given","C":"Ability to analyse benefi ts and harm","D":"Ability to retain information long enough to analyse them","E":"Ability to communicate a decision"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Capacity by defi nition is a legal concept; it refers to the ability to enter into valid contracts. Every adult is presumed to have capacity unless proved otherwise. Capacity is also task specifi c; one can have capacity to decide on treatment but can lack capacity to dispose of an estate. A test for capacity includes: (1) able to understand the nature of a decision that needs to be made; (2) able to weigh risks and benefi ts of any decision; (3) able to retain information long enough to make a decision; and (4) able to communicate the decision clearly. It is not necessary for the patient to believe in the information given to him. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 736."},{"question":"Which is the most important ethical principle underlying informed consent?","options":{"A":"Benefi cience","B":"Autonomy","C":"Non-malefi cience","D":"Justice","E":"Paternalism"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"For an informed consent to be valid, as a general rule, fi ve areas of information must be provided: (1) description of the medical condition or problem; (2) nature and purpose of the proposed treatment; (3) risks and benefi ts of the proposed treatment; (4) viable alternatives to the proposed treatment; and (5) prognosis with and without treatment. The most important ethical principle preserved by obtaining informed consent is that of patient autonomy. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1372."},{"question":"Over-riding patient confi dentiality cannot be substantiated reasonably if it is carried out under which of the following situations?","options":{"A":"Grave danger to a third party","B":"Disclosure of information is required by law","C":"Child protection involved","D":"Under court order","E":"Following the Death of the patient"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Personal information should not be disclosed to a third party without the patient’s express consent, except when: (1) serious risk to third parties outweighs the interests on patient’s privacy, for example child abuse; (2) disclosure of information is required by law, for example a notifi able disease; and (3) patient explicitly agrees to disclosure to a third party. Death of a patient does not waive one’s responsibility to maintain confi dentiality. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1387."},{"question":"Which of the following cannot be considered as an exception to direct informed consent?","options":{"A":"Waiver","B":"Detention under mental health act","C":"Emergencies where full information cannot be given","D":"Incompetent patient","E":"Passively compliant patient"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"When a person is passively compliant it is necessary to consider absence of informed consent. This is often seen when patients are prescribed ECT – without knowing all required information, they will agree for a course of treatment passively as the doctor has prescribed it. Legal privilege is the right to maintain secrecy or confi dentiality when summoned by court. The right of legal privilege belongs to the patient. Therapeutic privilege is different from this legal privilege. Therapeutic privilege is used when a psychiatrist withholds information in the belief that giving a patient all of the information would harm the patient. This is not commonly practised. While detaining a patient under the mental health act, often there is no consent from the patient for hospitalization. But this is commonly done against patient’s approval on the grounds of safety of the patient and the others. An incompetent person is one who is incapable of giving informed consent; in which case, consent can be granted only by that person’s guardian, or other persons with legal authority to give consent (e.g. a lasting power of attorney for health-care issues). Consent is presumed when a person is suffering from an emergent situation that requires treatment but is unable to give consent. Waiver is a situation where a patient asks the therapist not to give him a particular part of health information as that would be detrimental for him to know it. Again, this is rarely used. Kay J and Tasman A, eds. Essentials of Psychiatry. Wiley, 2006, p. 88.HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS 191"},{"question":"In ethology, imprinting refers to which of the following processes?","options":{"A":"Learning modifi ed by consequences","B":"Learning independent of developmental age","C":"Slow learning of parental behaviours","D":"Learning neonatal refl exes in human beings","E":"None of the above180 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Ethology refers to the biological study of animal behaviour. Imprinting is a specialized form of learning which occurs early in life (critical phase). The exposure to the stimulus situation must occur during the critical period, and the exposure can be of short duration without any reinforcement. This type of learning is particularly resistant to change. It has not been clearly demonstrated in human infants so far. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 160."},{"question":"If a patient reveals murderous intentions against his wife, a psychiatrist is duty bound to inform both police and the wife. This principle is derived from which of the following medicolegal illustrations?","options":{"A":"Tarasoff’s case","B":"Bournewood case","C":"McNaughten’s case","D":"Gillick’s case","E":"Shipman’s case"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Two months before killing his exgirlfriend Tarasoff, Poddar had declared his intentions to his psychotherapist. The psychotherapist tried to have Poddar detained but he was soon released. Police were informed of the risk, but the court ruled that apart from a duty of care to the patient, and duty to protect by informing the police, there is a duty to warn the third party directly. This is called the Tarasoff ruling. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1374."},{"question":"Which of the following best describes the difference between the terms handicap and impairment?","options":{"A":"Handicap refers to loss of social role","B":"Impairment refers to loss of social role","C":"Handicap refers to a structural defect","D":"Impairment refers to inability to perform a complex task","E":"Handicap refers to irreversible loss"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Impairment (I) is defi ned as any loss or abnormality of a bodily structure or function. Disability (D) is the restriction to perform an activity in a normal manner due to the impairment. The social disadvantage for a given individual in terms of role fulfi lment resulting from the disability is called handicap (H) (I leads to D; D leads to H). Reversibility of loss is not considered as a discriminating feature in defi ning handicap. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 688."},{"question":"Fathers of schizophrenia patients originate from higher social class than the patients themselves. This exemplifi es which of the following theories?","options":{"A":"Social causation","B":"Social disintegration","C":"Social drift","D":"Social labelling","E":"Social construction"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Goldberg conducted a survey of a national sample of males aged 25–34 on their fi rst admission to a mental hospital in England and Wales for schizophrenia. This showed an expected excess of patients in lower social class v Lower economic class was seen as a cause for schizophrenia (social causation). But when the social class distribution of the fathers at the time of the patients’ birth was studied, it transpired to be very similar to that of the general population. This is explained by the hypothesis that schizophrenia results in a downward drift of socioeconomic status rather than poverty being a cause for schizophrenia. (This social drift hypothesis was fi rst suggested by the Chicago study of Faris and Dunham, 1922–1934). Goldberg EM and Morrison SL. Schizophrenia and social class. British Journal of Psychiatry 1963; 109: 785–802."},{"question":"The Helsinki declaration is applicable in which of the following scenarios?","options":{"A":"A 24-year-old man is comatose and needs blood transfusion","B":"A 13-year-old girl asks for contraception","C":"A Jehovah’s witness refuses blood transfusion for his 5-year-old child","D":"A 34-year-old man volunteers for a neuroimaging study","E":"A 94-year-old lady refuses to move to a nursing home"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The Helsinki declaration is associated with research ethics. The efforts to streamline ethical principles of conducting research on human subjects started following the Second World War. Gillick competence refers to the assessment of ability of a child (16 years or younger) to consent to his or her own medical treatment, without the need for parental permission. Goodyear MDE, et al. The Declaration of Helsinki. British Medical Journal 2007; 335: 624–625."},{"question":"Which one of the following occupations carries a high risk of eating disorders?","options":{"A":"Modelling","B":"Law","C":"Nursing","D":"Marketing","E":"TeachingHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and ETHICS | QUESTIONS 181"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Ballet dancers and models have a high prevalence of anorexia nervosa as a result of pressures to sustain a slim fi gure consistent with their professional requirements. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 836."},{"question":"Under the principle of common law which of the following can be done without a patient’s consent?","options":{"A":"Blood sample can be drawn after paracetamol overdose in an emergency","B":"Liver transplantation can be done on a suicidal patient","C":"A psychiatric inpatient can be detained overnight if they attempt to leave","D":"Contraceptives can be implanted to a young lady with mania","E":"Depot antipsychotics could be given for agitation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Common law principle of necessity allows medical interventions only if they are life saving, emergency measures. Irreversible procedures such as transplantation cannot be carried out. It is not good practice to administer depot under ‘emergency’ situations. Psychiatric detention must follow Mental Health Act principles whenever required. Hewson B. The law on managing patients who harm themselves and deliberately refuse treatment. British Medical Journal 1999; 319: 905–907.192 HISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, and EDTHICS | ANSWERS"},{"question":"‘Run amok’ involves sudden dissociative reaction which can lead to multiple homicide or suicide. It is best classifi ed under which of the following categories?","options":{"A":"Dissociation reaction","B":"Somatoform disorders","C":"Culture-bound syndrome","D":"Substance use disorder","E":"Delusional disorder"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Running amok (derived from Malay word amuk, meaning ‘mad with anger’) is a Malaysian culture bound syndrome. It usually affects a young male who will develop a sudden frenzy and acquire a weapon in an attempt to kill or injure anyone indiscriminately. Amok episodes can lead to serious violence or suicide. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1063."},{"question":"Who fi rst used the word ‘psychiatry’ (or ‘psychiatrie’) to describe the profession?","options":{"A":"Reil","B":"Rush","C":"Deniker","D":"Kline","E":"Charcot"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Johann Christian Reil coined the term psychiatry to describe the practice of psychological medicine. He was a German doctor and used the word ‘Psychiatrie’ in 1808. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 20."},{"question":"One of the following is a major proponent of the antipsychiatry movement?","options":{"A":"William Osler","B":"Thomas Szasz","C":"Aubrey Lewis","D":"Henry Maudsley","E":"Adolf Meyer"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Thomas Szasz has expressed strong views against the current conceptual models of disease in psychiatry. Antipsychiatry refers to a heterogeneous school that challenges the fundamental theories and practices of psychiatry. Aubrey Lewis was an English psychiatrist associated with the Maudsley Hospital. Adolf Meyer proposed psychobiology. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 4 Table 1.2."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT routinely considered as boundary violations in a therapeutic relationship?","options":{"A":"Touching except handshake","B":"Treating friends or relatives","C":"Personal disclosure","D":"Interpretation of emotionally neutral statements","E":"Colluding with a patient against a third partyThis page intentionally left blankHISTORY, SOCIAL PSYCHIATRY, chapter and ETHICS 6 ANSWERS"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Interpretation is an interview technique and not a boundary violation. It is increasingly realized that subtle violations of doctor–patient boundaries often occur in psychiatric setting. Boundary crossing is defi ned as intentional or unintentional incursions occurring during a therapeutic relationship. When such boundary crossings produce harm to the patient, then they are called boundary violations. This can be both sexual and non-sexual violation. Kay J and Tasman A, eds. Essentials of Psychiatry. Wiley, 2006, p. 65, Table 5.5."}]');export{e as default};
